this is just
Speaker 1: amazing i mean hello somebody i don't know what to say every single week we have such incredible guests and we are learning so much and so i am beyond delighted like almost jumping out of my skin happy
Speaker 2: hello somebody to be with someone who i admire so
much
Speaker 2: very much who i hold in high regard and someone who we have built a relationship with one another i know is well past 10 years right now she is an incredible force of
Speaker 3: nature and her name is jennifer farmer she is known as the pr whisperer she's an author a lecturer baby and she has a podcast
Speaker 3: called The First and Only, which we are going to talk about her new book that's coming out titled The First and Only.
Speaker 4: And it really is about black women. It is a love letter to black women. And that love letter is very much needed in today's
Speaker 2: climate and is needed every single generation. And Jennifer Farmer, we have with
us...
my
Speaker 2: special advisor j3 himself so just in case if he wants to he might have a few things to say
Speaker 5: as we talk today how are you i am doing well and
Speaker 6: i'm so happy to uh to be looking for your podcast hello somebody i'm
Speaker 7: so glad to have you you have been with me through many
Speaker 3: moments highs and lows so this is certainly a great moment for us to share with folks how we first met
Speaker 1: How our incredible paths crossed and how we have been lifting and edifying one another ever since. And that magical moment happened in the Ohio
Speaker 3: Senate where I was serving as a state senator and you were the deputy chief of staff. That's right. Deputy chief
Speaker 2: of staff. I have campaign manager in my mind because you've done so much. You were the deputy. Well, that pretty much was like managing. You
had to
Speaker 2: manage us, though. You had to manage the senators. but definitely
Speaker 2: chief of staff for the Ohio Senate caucus and we have been going strong together ever since
Speaker 7: how was that experience and how did that experience set you on the path to what you are doing right now
so at that
Speaker 6: time I believe this was 2001 so that was more uh than 19 years
Speaker 8: ago and it remained so we've known each
Speaker 10: other actually for 19 years
- Oh
Speaker 10: my God,
Speaker 11: you have done it all. I mean, how in the world have you been able to do all of those things? And you are a mother as well. I remember your baby boy who's not such a baby anymore. -
Speaker 2: He's 21 now. - Oh my God, when we met, I remember he had such a love for
Speaker 11: art.
Speaker 11: And, and, and we did some things together to enrich him on the art side. I'm sure he doesn't remember that, but I'm just smiling from ear to ear thinking about he was just a little boy and now he's a grown young man. They'll always be our babies. But you're,
Speaker 12 (higher-pitched voice): you know what? You're absolutely right. And this just reminds me. So I think I had a
Speaker 8: laugh earlier because
Speaker 8: I've worked in the Senate twice when I first worked in the Senate, it was 2001. And I don't believe you were in the Senate at that time. I came in 2008. Exactly. And the second time when I came back as the deputy chief of staff, that was 2009.
Speaker 8: So you were right. We've known each other for about 11 years.
Speaker 14: I took us from 11 to 19, but you know, it's all good. All good. That's
Speaker 11: okay. I received it because the way we work, it seems like we've been together for a lifetime.
So I
Speaker 11: received those 19, I received those 19 years.
And you just
Speaker 11: had a
Speaker 3: plethora of experiences and I, with each and every opportunity that has been presented to you, you've been able to build
Speaker 3: on those experiences so much so that you put out your own shingle i know that's what attorneys say but you started your own pr firm
Speaker 1: spotlight pr pr yes you wrote a book about pr on a budget
Speaker 11: because it's so hard for small businesses and individuals who don't necessarily
Speaker 3: have a lot of money to be able to afford a pr specialist like yourself and so again you were So if you're thinking
about the
Speaker 3: woman and
Speaker 1: man, and even created a powerful guide for how folks can and should have a strong PR person.
Speaker 16: Absolutely. I
Speaker 8: mean, you know, I think that the only thing that we're responsible for is what we can do and the gifts and talents that each of us have. And I've decided that I'm going to live full and that I'm going to give back what God has given to me. And so when I guide, There will be no unused talents.
You
Speaker 8: know, God will not look at me and say, well, Jennifer, I gave you this and you didn't use it. He will say you have squeezed the life out
Speaker 17: of everything that I've given you, you know, and from that lens, you know, be proud and happy. I do
Speaker 18: believe that your life is you personify
Speaker 19: the ability to do well and to do good at the same time.
You can
Speaker 20: do well and you can do good at the
Speaker 8: same time. It does not have to be a trade off.
Speaker 8: particularly when you lean into the gifts that come
Speaker 17: to you so easily so for instance with you you are a phenomenal speaker
uh
Speaker 8: you you can take a complex issue and not only make it understandable to the masters but to get people fired up that's a gift
and if we
Speaker 8: lean into the gifts that we have
then you
Speaker 8: definitely can do well and do good at the same
Speaker 21: time
And
Speaker 22: that, to me, is an obligation for people to do that. To find their purpose and to just saturate in that thing and try not to get caught up in what other people are doing and how fabulous it may seem their lives are and focus on what the Creator is. We're believers, and I know some people don't necessarily believe in that way, but what the Creator, the universe, what forces,
Speaker 22: are calling you to do good, to do great things. And once you find that, you know, there
Speaker 23: is a way to make a living from doing good.
One of
Speaker 16: the best pieces of advice that I've ever
Speaker 8: received, it came from the dean of my college. He's now passed away, Dean Paul Burgett.
And I
Speaker 21: remember I was a sophomore or a junior in college, and I was really stressing about,
Speaker 21: how i was going to make money i don't know why i was worried about this but i was
Speaker 8: stressing and dean bergett said don't worry about the money do what you love and the money will come and whenever i got to a point in my career where i was worried or where you know i was going to entertain worry i would think about what he said is do what you love and the money will come and And that has been so true.
for me
Speaker 8: professionally yes and
Speaker 22: i can certainly relate to that as you as you well know too so i'm sure a lot of people can definitely relate to that do practicing your gifts and just know that it's coming that reward so to speak is coming and it's okay to live a good life i think so many especially jennifer working class people poor people they're struggling every single day and you get to a point sometimes where you don't feel like you are deserving and moments in your life where you don't believe
Speaker 22: that you are worthy of
Speaker 24: actually living a good life.
I
Speaker 16: think that
when you come
Speaker 16: from a community and when you've seen other people struggle, or perhaps when you've
Speaker 8: struggled, you can question whether or not that is your life experience or whether that is supposed to be your life experience. And when you get to the point where you start having a level of success that can change your day-to-day,
it can
Speaker 8: be tempting you know you could feel guilty but what i say and what i pray is you know god bless me to be a blessing to others to be a blessing to myself and my family but to be a blessing to others i want to be the person who can give i want to be the person who sees something that is worth investing in and have the means and the capacity to do
so hello
Speaker 26: and body on that yeah and you
Speaker 6: know and the great thing is is
A lot
Speaker 6: of times we think that we have to start. We have to
Speaker 8: wait until we get exactly where everything is exactly perfect. And that is not true. I think you start from where you are and you do what you can with where you have. And in time, it may grow. But even if it never does, there's always something that you can do
Speaker 21: from where you are.
That's it. I
Speaker 27: totally agree. I say that all the time. Do what you can where you are, what you have.
Speaker 27: what you have yeah
Speaker 22: we all we all have a level we all have something that we can do no matter what level we may be on and no matter what we may be dealing with in our day-to-day lives we can all do something so i oh my god i live by that as well we pray that similar the same prayer not just similar the same prayer jennifer farmer we do
Speaker 22: Oh, my God. I want people to absorb this because
Speaker 28: it is such a heavy time right now, as you and I know, from the COVID pandemic that has engulfed not only our country, but the entire world. We are approaching 50 million people unemployed as we speak, which is so unbelievable, sad, heavy.
Speaker 28: And we know that a lot of those folks will not have health insurance because their health insurance is tied to their employment, which begs the question, why do we continue to do things in that way? And so that's the pandemic. And then right there in the swirl of the pandemic.
We
Speaker 28: have civil unrest that has been bubbling up for weeks in the United States of America has taken hold. This entire movement has taken hold internationally as well, coming off of being being sparked by the murder of George Floyd. But we also know there are other names that are within that.
Speaker 28: That moment that has caused people to say, particularly the
Speaker 29: African-American community, in the words of our dear Fannie Lou Hamer, I'm sick and tired of being sick and tired, sick and
Speaker 28: tired. And you work a lot in that space.
Speaker 28: Jennifer, from working with or working for the advancement project to even in your own firm, you do a lot of training about racial bias and particularly implicit bias and anti-blackness. Share with us, because you are an expert in that issue today.
Speaker 28: And I feel like we are at a synergistic moment where more people, they're open to having some of the harder conversations that this country has not been willing to have. And then on a micro level, just even individuals have not wanted to have. But it's just something about this particular moment where we have an opportunity to go deep. So I want to go deep with you. This is your not only your your area expertise, but it is your passion and how you are able to peel back the layers. I've been in trainings
with you.
Speaker 28: with you i mean you did a
Speaker 22: training for the sanders campaign as well at at my request but that's a whole nother
Speaker 28: story
for
Speaker 22: another time
Speaker 28: talk to all of us speak to us about racism itself implicit bias and anti-blackness one
of the things that i
Speaker 30: think organizations and people We'll be right back.
fail
Speaker 30: at or make mistakes in is they they think because they have noble aspirations because they proclaim progressive values that their work is done and when you talk about race race has to be addressed on an individual level as well as a collective and a structural level you can't say you can't say well you know i i want to
Speaker 8: be anti-racist
And so
Speaker 8: I'm going to go and work for this organization, but not do the work to transform yourself. It doesn't work like that.
Any person
Speaker 8: who was born in the United States, who has lived here, who has spent any length of time, they
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): are impacted by race.
And so
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): in anti-racism, it has to be unlearned.
When I
Speaker 30: worked for Advancement Projects, probably one of the best aspects of that experience was really grounding in what anti-blackness is.
And
Speaker 32: when
Speaker 30: I think about the animosity and the hatred that you see towards people of color, it is rooted in that person having an ounce of blackness. It's rooted in anti-blackness.
So if
Speaker 30: there were no anti-blackness, I don't believe that we would have the hostility that many Latin American immigrants face. It's all rooted in anti-blackness. I also think that you can't
just say
Speaker 30: that you're anti-racist and
you can't
Speaker 30: just do the work. You have to examine the way that racism has been internalized within yourself.
And
Speaker 30: so there is work for each and every one of us to do. Even black people can harbor internalized oppression and anti-blackness. And sometimes we see that show up in
Speaker 33: colorism. Sometimes we see it show up in dating preferences.
Speaker 30: Sometimes we'll see it show up in even how we care for our bodies and how we care for the messages that we send to ourselves. Every day, we have to understand that in this country, it is inherently racist. And no, black people can't be racist because racism is about power. It's about structural power.
But
Speaker 30: we do have to understand that, you know, we still have work to do to ensure, to erase internalized oppression. And if you wonder how that shows
up, our
Speaker 30: entire system is set up to despise Black people. From the images that we see to what we're taught from children about what is beautiful and what is not, to what is smart and what is not, to who has capacity and who does
not, it's
Speaker 30: rooted in race.
Speaker 30: And so we all have, we're all on the journey. The question is, are you running? The question is, are you continually making paths and strides forward? And in this day and age, there's simply no excuse to say, I don't, you know, I don't know where to start.
There's so
Speaker 30: many wonderful resources and books like I love.
Speaker 30: Uh, so you want to talk about race. I love, uh, white fragility. There's so many different books. I love, uh, Ibram Kendi's, um, how to be anti-racist. There's so many wonderful resources. I also think that the moment that you open your mind and you open your heart and you put out in the universe, your commitment to doing better, your commitment to learning, I believe that people show up and
and
Speaker 30: and help you along your journey and point to areas where you can be enlightened and
Speaker 8: so one of the reasons that i do this work is i think that as a black person in america you have to do the work to stay sane you have to do the work to uh to live a happy life you have to do the work to
Speaker 34: counter the many messages that you get that you are not good enough you are not smart enough you are not beautiful enough you are not worthy enough
Speaker 35: Jennifer, you're preaching down so many streets right now. You and I could do at least 10 other shows
Speaker 29: based on everything you just said. I am bubbling over right now with emotion. As you know,
Speaker 4: you and I have had many a conversation, many a tearjerker over anti-blackness, over microaggressions,
over...
the
Speaker 4: fact that this society is set up that way, the systemic racism, the system-wide racism that still exists that exhibits itself all the time. And it is all of
Speaker 1: those microaggressions that build and build and build and build. And it's so wonder that black people as a collective
Speaker 1: as a collective have not just totally
Speaker 22: combusted it really is I saw a meme the other day and it said something it read something like America is lucky that black people only want justice and not revenge because of all that we have endured and that we continue to endure in this country and your point about colorism which is leading me exactly where I want to go because this love letter that you've written to black women, the first and only, but colorism has been
Speaker 22: one of my heavy burdens you know being a chocolate chocolate sister and just experiencing
Speaker 29: those things you know being a child of the you know I was born in the late 60s and so it was coming of age in high school in the 80s and I remember you know not being able to quote unquote buy a date because I wasn't a light-skinned sister and I didn't have good hair and then dark skin came
Speaker 22: in with Wesley Snipes you know
Speaker 22: We got to kind of joke about that a little bit just to continue to function. But you are absolutely right. I have horror stories. I remember Jennifer being in elementary school and one of my lighter skinned classmates, we were standing in line and we were on our way to a field trip. And I don't
Speaker 29: know, just out of the blue, she took her hand and she rubbed it across my face. And then she rubbed her same hand across her face and she said something like, my skin, meaning her skin.
Speaker 29: skin was softer than mine because she was lighter than me now this was an elementary school and I'm sure her parents didn't sit her down and tell her that but it was those images those messages that you that you were talking about that got into her subconscious that she really thought she was better than
Speaker 4: me and imagine the life that I had to live every single day you know every year really and and just coming to believe that in my my
Speaker 3: psyche was was was messed up
Speaker 3: Because over the course of my life, I am constantly reminded, even to this day, that
Speaker 1: the lighter you are, the more beautiful you have seen, the closer to white you are, the more your beauty is elevated
Speaker 4: and projected and put out there. And that if you don't have those Eurocentric attributes, somehow you are lacking. And so multiply me by millions of little black girls.
Speaker 4: black boys but particularly black girls because of the way the society is set up who somehow believe that they were less worthy because they are not as close to white and i say that even as an accomplished black woman that i still harbor that pain that kind of pain to
Speaker 22: this day and i want to share one other story with you and and i and i want you to weigh in on what i'm talking about just one
Speaker 1: other quick story when i was in high
school
And
Speaker 1: I tried out for a play and I was really good. Folks might not know this about me. We're going to reveal some
Speaker 11: things. Sister was good. You know, my drama class, baby, I was good. I could Panama my behind off. I was just good like that. And so we
Speaker 3: were having tryouts for a play. I was in the ninth grade. I remember this like it was yesterday. I was in the ninth grade and the play was Charlie Brown. And so I tried out for the character of Lucy.
And I
Speaker 3: did
Speaker 11: that. I mean, if I must say so myself, I did that thing. Jennifer, Jen, I gave a performance of a lifetime and I knew, have you ever done something you just walk off, you just know you did that. And so, you know, they put the, after a while, in a couple of days, they'll post on the wall who
Speaker 3: won what parts.
Speaker 3: And I was devastated. I didn't get the part of Lucy. So I went to my drama teacher and I asked the question, what happened? Because I knew I did that. And he said to me, he said, you know, Nina, you did. You were absolutely the best. But Lucy ain't black. Wow. Wow. Wow.
Oh, you
Speaker 3: talking about being crushed. Lucy
Speaker 37: ain't black. I'm just going to let you take it. Go on and take it. Take it over from me.
Speaker 38: So.
I think
Speaker 38: that every day that we live has
to be
Speaker 38: an act of resistance. And part of what
Speaker 8: we're resisting is not just the messages that we receive today or the messages that we received yesterday, but the cumulative impact of the messages that we've received our entire lives. I recently went to Atlanta and I took my babysitter who is in her early 20s
And
Speaker 8: she's a dark skin, dark skin sister. And somehow we got on a conversation and
I asked
Speaker 8: her, she's very, very bright. I was asking her about, you know, high school. And she told, she told me something that I will never forget. And she said that
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): it was miserable. And she said it was miserable. And she said every day of my senior year, I was called a nigger.
Speaker 21: every day oh my god and she said that um you know as a dark skinned girl she said that it
Speaker 30: was very clear
Speaker 8: to her that no one wanted to date her uh she also told me that she when she finally was invited to the crime she was really really excited
about it only
Speaker 33: to have her hope gas to find out that someone told the guy someone made a bet with
the guy on
Speaker 33: to ask her out it was not sincere Thank you.
And
Speaker 33: she told me that it was not until she went to a historically black college
Speaker 8: that she came, she started to say, okay, well, maybe these messages that I've heard about my skin are not true.
And I've heard
Speaker 30: similar messages from my brother, who's a lot darker. I
Speaker 8: remember us growing up and the things that people would say to him.
And
Speaker 8: also, in my family, you know, our family ran the rainbow. We have people who are very, very fair-skinned, and we have people who are very, very dark.
And so
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): all of this, I remember.
And, you know,
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): the only thing that I can say is it's very, very painful. People used to say, sticks and stones can break my
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): bones, words can never hurt, and that's just a lie. Yeah.
because
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): once you've heard these things you don't you can't unhear you know and so it's it's i feel like it's a constant resisting
Speaker 8: the messages and then in addition to like resisting the messages that we hear
it's also
Speaker 33: thinking about okay well how do we see um how
do we
Speaker 33: move beyond it and not get uh resentful
And
Speaker 33: for me, I
Speaker 8: remember, you know, my son's father, when he decided to marry, his wife was very fair, or she is very fair. And I
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): remember thinking, okay, everyone in his family is fair. I was just too dark.
And, you
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): know, so we have all these
Speaker 33: questions. And I finally got to the point.
Speaker 33: Where I said, you know what, I'm just going to accept who I am. And every day, you know, you watch TV and you see the movies and there's a black
Speaker 8: family. The father is dark and his wife is very, very fair. And then their kid, their son is dark and the daughter is fair. I was like, what
Speaker 30: message are you really trying to send us? And so...
I
Speaker 30: resist that. And I do it continually. It's not enough to just do it once. You have to do it
Speaker 40: every time the emotion, every time the pain rises up.
Amen to
Speaker 41: that, Jen. I'm sighing deeply here. What you said, every day that we live has to be
Speaker 29: an act of resistance. Amen
Speaker 4: to that. And we don't talk enough about colorism. We talk about racism in a very generic way. We are starting to talk about anti-racism.
Speaker 4: anti-blackness, and then within all of that is the whole notion of colorism and the impact. I remember the powerful speech that Lupita gave during a luncheon for Essence magazine, and she recounted how she felt as being a dark-skinned black woman.
Speaker 42 (higher-pitched voice): I hope that my presence on your screens and in magazines may lead you, young girl, on a similar journey.
That
Speaker 42 (higher-pitched voice): you will feel the validation of your external beauty, but also get to the deeper business of being beautiful inside that
There is no
Speaker 43: shade in that beauty. Thank you What
it meant
Speaker 29: for her to be where she is
Speaker 29: today and understanding
Speaker 4: the symbol that she carries a big burden because there are so many other dark-skinned people, particularly dark-skinned black people and black women in particular. And I'm not saying that black men don't go through that as well because they do, but because of the way that our society...
Speaker 4: reflects or or puts out portrays beauty it impacts women in a different and and deeper way
Speaker 29: but anybody that is darker skinned certainly understands what you and i are talking about and it really is so superficial
Speaker 1: but it goes back to how the eurocentric world view of beauty permeates
Speaker 1: Everything. The entire world has adopted those
Speaker 29: standards of beauty. It is one of the reasons why black women, why we relax our hair. It is one of the reasons why we go through generational iterations of what I would call black power consciousness, where there is a resistance to European standards of beauty. And I'm really glad to see that reemerge right now in our time with so many black women.
Speaker 29: reclaiming their natural hair texture. And I'm certainly not one of those that believes if you got to furrow you down and if you relax your hair, you're not. What I do affirm though, a lot
Speaker 1: of the things we do to ourselves as black women, we don't do it in a conscious way. We relax our hair because we were taught before birth that again, that the closer you are to the Eurocentric standard of beauty,
For
Speaker 1: example, having straight hair. This, in fact, makes you more
Speaker 29: appealing and more beautiful. And there's just a consciousness that is that that's out there percolating. That is very powerful, Jennifer. And I hope that it continues and that black women know however you come is fine. But for some for society to tell you that the hair that you were born with is not good enough. That's heavy.
Speaker 44: Yeah. And the messages come up in a variety of different formats. Oh, your hair is difficult or your hair is not
Speaker 8: manageable.
Speaker 8: you have to you have to um you have to relax it or there's something wrong with your hair and when people tell you there's something wrong with any aspects of yourself what they're saying is there's something wrong with you and so the messages that we received about our hair that we received about you know our full lips that
we received
Speaker 8: about our nose that we
Speaker 33: received about our body i mean women are so analyzed black women are so analyzed you you were telling a story about a play, I remember.
Speaker 33: And this one that I'm going to share with you, it was from a black teacher. But I remember going to tryouts for the track team. And I was really excited because I wanted to, I wanted to run. And I remember running and I thought, okay, you know, maybe it wasn't the fastest, but that was fun. And, uh, telling, you know, being really excited and the teacher saying, oh, well, you'll never be a runner. Your, your butt is too big. And I was maybe 12. I mean, I was, I was in middle school.
And
Speaker 33: those words stuck with me. Similarly, I remember wanting to try out for ballet and the teacher saying something about my body.
And what
Speaker 33: I've done, you know, and what I'm mindful of, not only as
Speaker 17: an active resistance for myself, but I now have a daughter, is I don't comment on my body.
You know, so if I
Speaker 17: feel like I've gained weight,
Speaker 33: I don't acknowledge it.
If
Speaker 33: I see a part of my body that I would like changed,
then
Speaker 6: I speak to that part and I speak lovingly to that part. But my daughter will never hear me loathing my body because I don't want to transfer that to her. And that's regardless
Speaker 8: of the size that I am. I'm always going to find a way to say something positive.
Speaker 8: until I get to a point where they're genuine and deep appreciation with the hope that regardless of what she hears in the world, she can say, I never heard my mom complain that she was, you know, that she was not the right size. I never heard my mom complain that this part of her body was too big or too small. We just didn't, I don't want her to hear that.
Well,
Speaker 47: you talk about a love letter that is using the word show enough as my grandmother
Speaker 29: would, that is show enough,
Speaker 47: right?
Speaker 47: a
Speaker 29: beautiful thing and how how blessed she is to have you live
Speaker 35: that out loud and you you recently went through transformation with your with your hair
Speaker 48: too definitely yeah yeah definitely you know what you were saying
Speaker 33: about relaxed hair for years I felt like
Speaker 8: okay well there's something wrong with my hair and in order to be accepted
I need
Speaker 8: to have my hair I need to have a relaxer
Speaker 33: Well, I stopped getting relaxers in 2013, but I still wanted that straight look. And so every week, and
if I
Speaker 33: couldn't go every week, every other week,
Speaker 8: I went to the stylist. He would flat iron my hair. He would do a curl, you know, put the blow dryer in it.
And I
Speaker 8: would have the same effect, hair that was really, really straight.
And over
Speaker 8: time, you know, I would ask myself, okay, why are you doing it? And what does it say about you if you don't do it?
Yeah.
With
Speaker 8: all of this transformation and as I identify areas in my life that need to change or as I'm just aware of different thoughts patterns, I'm trying to deal with myself as gently and as lovingly as possible. So when I've noticed things, I try not to condemn myself and I try not to make self-condemnation a habit. And
so I
Speaker 8: would just notice these things and I would be curious
Speaker 6: about it. And
then I just
Speaker 33: started thinking,
Speaker 6: you know what? Yeah.
Speaker 6: I've thought about changing my hair for a while. I've thought about going natural, truly
Speaker 49: natural. And
what
Speaker 6: I decided was that I decided to
Speaker 30: grow locks.
And I
Speaker 30: started growing locks in March of 2020. And I'm going to continue to do so. And
part
Speaker 8: of the thinking for me is, and part of the process is questioning what is beautiful.
And
Speaker 8: developing my own standards for what is for what is beautiful, but also distancing myself from the need to be seen as beautiful in the eyes of others if I'm comfortable with myself.
Speaker 47: Hello, somebody. And that takes a great deal of not only self-reflection, but actual
Speaker 29: courage because you are resisting.
in
Speaker 29: your own way as an individual and then there are others who do it for their own reasons too but it is a resistance
Speaker 4: to what this country and what the world says the standards of beauty are and that I mean that really takes a lot Jennifer and I just commend you so very much and just the healthy outlook that you have and that didn't happen overnight you had to
Speaker 4: deconstruct your construction and do that every day and i'm sure you still even in this transformation probably still have moments where you have to do the self-talk to remind yourself that you are doing this for yourself first and foremost you're doing it for all the right reasons and you are a symbol not only to your baby girl but to other black women who constantly
Speaker 4: question their value and their beauty in this society their worth which is tied to a whole lot and it just reminds in in the 1940s you made me think about psychologists kenneth and mamie clark both dr clarks you may recall they did they did an experiment they conducted an experiment to to examine the psychological effects that segregation had on black children and it was it was called it's It's known as
the doll test.
Speaker 4: Which
Speaker 50: doll is the black doll and
which one
Speaker 50: is the white doll?
That one.
Speaker 51: And they used some dolls. I think it was about four dolls and all of the dolls looked
Speaker 4: exactly alike. The only thing that was different about these dolls was their complexion, the tone on the dolls.
Speaker 4: All of the subjects, I think they examined children who were in the age range from three to seven years old.
And
Speaker 51: they were asked, all of the dolls were set up and they asked them questions. And why
Speaker 52: is that doll pretty?
Because
Speaker 53: he's white and he has two eyes.
Which doll is the
Speaker 54: ugly doll?
Why is that
Speaker 54: doll ugly?
Speaker 55: Because he's black.
Speaker 56: And...
Speaker 56: To a child, they picked time and
Speaker 51: time again that white doll. And why did they do that? I mean, all of the positive characteristics were assigned to the white doll.
Speaker 57: Because that's what they were taught. That's
Speaker 51: what they were
Speaker 58: taught. Subliminal.
Speaker 57: Sometimes,
Speaker 33: like, I don't feel like parents have to be perfect. Sometimes it's just small steps. And I remember when I was a little girl, my dad would take me and my sister and my brother. He took
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): us toy shopping every two weeks. Every time he got paid, he took us toy shopping and we could get one thing.
Speaker 30: And I remember as a girl, when I would go and get the doll, and sometimes we were drawn to the white doll, my dad would say, why don't you want this one?
Speaker 33: She's pretty. And he pushed us gently into getting the black doll. And so we had a ton of black dolls growing up. And when I had my daughter, I said, okay, she only gets dolls who look like her.
And so
Speaker 59: if you give Jennifer's
Speaker 21: daughter...
a
Speaker 21: doll and the doll does not look like her we're going to donate that doll or we're going to give it back
every
Speaker 29: day that we live has to be an act of resistance Jennifer Farmer said that
Speaker 21: it's an act of resistance and so I remember someone gave someone gave my
Speaker 8: daughter two dolls and one was white and my sister just started laughing and she said oh they clearly don't know you and I said no they don't and uh and we we donated it was around Christmas and we donated the doll and that's you but that's that is, uh,
Speaker 8: I can't control what happens outside of my
Speaker 33: house and even inside the house. You can't control everything, but I try to
be
Speaker 8: aware and I'm trying to raise my daughter as intentionally as possible. And
Speaker 60: so her, her dolls look like her and if they're old enough, then I will, you know, I will explain it.
Speaker 61: Absolutely. And you are influencing her and she will be an influence on others. And hopefully there will be a ripple
Speaker 62: effect.
Speaker 31 (higher-pitched voice): and my my goal for her is to teach her to love herself and i want
Speaker 33: her to love herself and i have to love myself so having a daughter has been it's been
a huge
Speaker 33: growth growth curve because i can't i can't lead her to where i have not been and so i
Speaker 8: say you know
i want
Speaker 8: to love myself that she loves herself but i want to love myself because i am god's gift you know apart from her
Speaker 63: There it is. It's just
Speaker 29: amazing. And, you know, it's mainstream society is basically co-opted our culture, our swag, if you will, although it was never good enough for us. I mean, people are getting lip injections, butt injections, just, you know, and making mega money off of what we naturally have for the most part. I mean, none of us, we're not homogeneous in our body types either, but there is a cultural
problem.
Type
Speaker 29: in terms of how you know our hips and behinds and lips and noses are different from the European and but
but now
Speaker 29: I mean this this thing has been happening where people appropriate have been appropriating our culture and and monetizing it in ways where those same black women were told that they were not.
Speaker 29: So I applaud you, Jennifer, for all that you are doing, both on a personal level and a professional level to make this world a better place, which leads me to an idea, something that you wrote. You
are a
Speaker 29: writer. You're a prolific writer. You have a blog and one of your blogs, Assertive Communication. I feel like everything that we've been talking about today.
Speaker 29: falls into that realm in some way. The way our hair looks, the way we dress, all of that communicates something. The way we respond to situations, it communicates something about ourselves and the society that we live in. And so the title was The Underbelly of Assertive Communications. And you wrote, I learned that sometimes perceptions to communication styles could be genderized and racialized.
Speaker 29: A white person could say something and would be perceived one way and I could say the same thing and be
Speaker 64: perceived an entirely different way.
In writing that
Speaker 1: blog, to me, you were building, it was a building block to your new book.
Speaker 1: titled First and Only, A Black Woman's Guide to Thriving. Let's go on and live
Speaker 29: in this space for a
Speaker 1: minute. Let's live here. Let's live here. Yeah, let's stay
Speaker 65: here. Let's visit here for a minute. I
wrote
Speaker 66: First and Only, A Black Woman's Guide to Thriving as I was
Speaker 30: analyzing different professional experiences that I was having. And, you know, when you're interested in something, you read as much as you can in that
Speaker 33: area.
Speaker 33: I've always been interested in leadership. I've always been interested in how people become CEOs, how they move up the ladder. And so I would read a lot of leadership books.
And I
Speaker 33: would be very fulfilled from these books.
Speaker 33: would go into different work situations or work experiences. And I would find that even though I read these books,
They
Speaker 33: could only take me so far. And what I realized is that many of the leadership and the management books that exist today were
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): written by white men, white men over 50, and then were written by white women. And when these
books were
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): written, they did not speak to the racism that black women experienced or the
Speaker 30: sexism that black women experienced.
And
Speaker 30: so they could only take me so far.
Speaker 33: They weren't speaking to the ways that I was seeing black women judged based on our tone, based on our appearance, based on even our bodies and what
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): we wore. And so you take a principle like, you know, it's important to be assertive. That's a principle that you will see in many leadership books.
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): What you won't see is the reaction that many Black women get when they are assertive. And assertive is about being able to say what works for you and what does not work for you. It's about being able to articulate your needs. It's about being able to stand with and for yourself. And I noticed, you know, as someone who would, you know, try to take a stand with and for myself, that depending on the
Speaker 30: environment that I was in, people would not like that.
What
Speaker 30: they wanted is they wanted the docile Jennifer who lived to serve everyone else except for
Speaker 8: herself. They wanted the person who was willing to sacrifice herself in service of everyone else. They wanted the person who would
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): just say yes, even when it was apparent that she could not do it.
And
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): so the underbelly of assertive communication is that
Speaker 30: while we say we want assertive communication, we have to make space for what that looks like based on a person's race, their gender, and their professional experience.
And so in
Speaker 30: my book,
Speaker 33: I talk about, you know, assertive communication. I talk about something called the ask penalties.
Speaker 33: We're all told that a closed mouth won't get fed and that you should ask for what you need.
But I have
Speaker 33: found that as a black woman, there have been times when I've articulated what I've needed or what I wanted, and people took exception to that.
And when I
Speaker 33: say the ask penalty,
Speaker 8: I'm not just referring to major things like asking for a raise or asking for a certain amount of vacation time before
Speaker 6: you take a job. I'm talking about...
Speaker 6: that as well as saying what works for you and what doesn't articulating a vision for your child you know what you want for your child so when i take my daughter to the
the
Speaker 33: the doctor i want to know what you're i want to know what they're doing i'm going to ask questions about that and you know i want people to be able to be comfortable
with that
Speaker 33: and if they're not then i'm willing to live
in that
Speaker 33: uh that discomfort when
i go
Speaker 33: to church Thank you.
I
Speaker 33: don't leave my critical thinking skills at home. I'm always questioning. I'm always wondering. And I want to be able to assert what I need.
So when I
Speaker 8: wrote first and only, I was speaking to the experience that a lot of Black women have when they show up as the first in a space, when they reach a certain pinnacle of success and they're the only person there, when they're the only
Speaker 33: person to hold that leader, like what they experience and then how they overcome.
and
Speaker 33: I would be remiss if I did not tell your audience how grateful I am that you wrote the foreword for the book and when I tell you the foreword is just
Speaker 39 (higher-pitched voice): beautiful it moves me to tears it's just it's phenomenal so thank you for
Speaker 67: that it's my
Speaker 22: high honor Jennifer you got me tearing up
Speaker 22: Right now, this is a
Speaker 4: book that we certainly need. It is a love letter to black women and to people who love black women. And so we want folks to go out and not only purchase your book, but gift it to somebody who needs it. Who may need to have Jennifer's voice speak a word of life into them to give them more encouragement.
to
Speaker 4: go along
Speaker 1: this journey called life. Jennifer Farmer, you really are the PR whisperer. You are, you know, people don't understand how skilled, you know, I often say black girl magic is real, but we work like hell to get it. That's the part that they don't know. It's real, but we work like hell to get it. You are indeed an author, a lecturer, a leading professional in communication strategy. You actually care so deeply and so much.
Speaker 1: You are a professional. You are a bright light. You are a force of nature. Thank you. And the little blur, I just got to, because
Speaker 11: this touched me so much as I was reading through your book. People must get the book. I want them on the edge of their seats about this book and her podcast. I hope that Jennifer gets a chance to do something with this on TV at some point.
Speaker 3: I put that into the universe because so many black,
Speaker 3: women need to hear this message but other people who love black women need to hear this message people who just love humanity need to hear this message but you dedicated this book to your daughter and to your nieces and this is what you said this is it this is it this is this is it right
Speaker 11: here hello somebody I want everybody to just kind of rest right here with Jennifer
Speaker 1: and myself
you
Speaker 1: You said, these words leap off the pages of your book in your dedication to your daughter and to your nieces. May you go without being asked, speak without seeking permission, and create
Speaker 11: without fear of failure. Woo! Woo! Now, if that don't light your soul on fire, I don't know what will. Black women, go without being asked, speak without seeking permission, and create failure.
Speaker 69: Without fear of failure, Jennifer, Father. Yes, I want my
Speaker 70: daughter. I dedicated the book to my daughter, and I have five beautiful nieces, and I dedicated it to them. And they are all in
Speaker 71: their 20s. I have one who's probably around 18 years.
But
Speaker 71: the other ones, my other nieces are in their 20s and they're just
Speaker 72: starting out in their, you know, careers.
And I want
Speaker 73: them to walk into space and say, we can do this because we don't know our
Speaker 71: aunt. You know, we saw what our aunt did.
And my
Speaker 71: nieces, they were my babies before I had my daughter. They were my baby girls before I had my daughter. And I have such a love and appreciation for black women. And I absolutely adore my nieces.
Speaker 71: And I want them to, you know, I
Speaker 73: want them to say we can because she did and because she did and because she did. And I want them to to move forward with that legacy,
Speaker 61: move forward, that legacy and grace and power
Speaker 3: and black girl magic.
Speaker 3: this has been this has been a word y'all listen please jennifer how how can folks uh connect with you your website social media so you can
Speaker 12 (higher-pitched voice): follow me on instagram and twitter at pr underscore whisperer and on facebook
at
Speaker 17: pr whisperer that's how you can find me on social media for first and only a black woman's guide to thriving you can order that from broadly books
Speaker 17: amazon or any other bookseller and then you know if you are interested in pr and you want to hear about that you can order that from any bookseller any book retailer all
Speaker 75: kinds of hotness going on jennifer farmer thank you so much you know how much i adore you darling i love me some jennifer
farmer i
Speaker 75: want the world to know i love
you too there it is
Hello Somebody is
Speaker 77: a production of Large Media Network. Our logo and web design was created by Grayson Co. Special thanks to other members of the Hello Somebody team. Tiffany Hale, Pepper Chambers, the Hot One, Julia Griffin, Angelo Greco, and Anna Mesa. Now, if you would like to support our production, please become a member on Patreon.com forward slash Hello Somebody. And finally, come join us for more conversation on my social media channels at Nina Turner.